A Guide to the St. Andrew's Catholic School Enrollment Records, 1897-1941, 1944-1953
Roanoke Public Libraries
Roanoke Public Libraries
St. Andrew's Catholic School Enrollment Records 1897-1941, 1944-1953
Roanoke Public Libraries
2005.4.3.3
1 oversize flat document box containing 3 volumes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection is copied with permission from the St. Andrew's Historical Society.
Alternative Form Available
Original enrollment records are maintained at the St. Andrew's Catholic Historical Society
Historical Information
When St. Andrew's Church was first established in 1882, its first pastor, Father Lynch, felt strongly that the church should invest in a school. The first school building was opened in 1889 and was called the Hall or Little School. It was a two story framed structure on the south end of the church property. Lay members served as educators at the first school, with boys being taught downstairs and the girl's classes upstairs. In order to secure the longevity of the school and build an adequate facility, Lynch agreed to open an orphan asylum, a priority for the Richmond Diocese. The orphanage was opened on the grounds. The Sisters who ran the Asylum also ran the school. Beginning in 1893 under the leadership of Sister Mary Vincent Hardie, the orphanage and school opened and operated out of the first Saint Vincent's building. The school and asylum operated as a single institution until 1931 when they were split. The orphanage became Saint Vincent's and the school became known as St. Andrew's Catholic School. The high school that was built in 1931 is still used as part of Roanoke Catholic, with additions to the school being built in the 1990's. The school remains a leader in Catholic school education. It was listed among the top 50 Catholic schools in the United States in 2004.
Scope and Content
St. Andrew's Catholic School Enrollment Records document the names of students who attended the school 1897-1941, 1944-1953. Lists of high school graduates are documented from 1897-1941. From 1897 through 1930, names of students and addresses are recorded. Award winners for typing and other accreditations are listed in Book 1 (no date). From 1926-1936, 1944-1953, there is a complete listing of school students (circa 1930-1936, class year is not listed at the top of the page) for all grades. Beginning in Book 2 pg 69, the lists are divided by grade and include the students' name, age, date of birth, father's name, address, occupation, phone number, and withdrawal information.
Arrangement
Records are arranged chronologically by graduation dates.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Index Terms
St. Andrew's Catholic School; School enrollment; Roanoke, Virginia
Contents List
- Book 1, 1897-1949. (Box 1)
  Bound volume with subsections. No index.
  - St. Andrew's High School Graduates, 1897-1941, 1948.
  - Winners of Special Credential Certificate and Admission to Order of Accurate Typists. No date.
  - School Enrollment numbers, 1917-1924.
  - Notes on Students, 1916-1924.
  - Commercial Graduates, 1939-1949.
- Book 2, 1926-1936. (Box 1)
  - St. Andrew's School Enrollment, every grade, 1926-1936.
    Beginning on page 69, records include each students name, age, date of birth, father's name, address, occupation, phone number and withdrawal information.
- Book 3, 1944-1953. (Box 1)
  - St. Andrew's School Enrollment, 1944-1953.
    Records include each student's name, age, date of birth, father's name, address, occupation, phone number and withdrawal information.